<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Steady Trekker</title><link href="https://steadytrekker.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://steadytrekker.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://steadytrekker.com/</id><updated>2023-01-20T08:36:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>Trail of the Coeur d'Alenes and Route of the Hiawatha</title><link href="https://steadytrekker.com/trail-of-the-coeur-dalenes-and-route-of-the-hiawatha.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-01-20T08:36:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-01-20T08:36:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Jeremy Monroe</name></author><id>tag:steadytrekker.com,2023-01-20:/trail-of-the-coeur-dalenes-and-route-of-the-hiawatha.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04365.jpg" alt="A pomeranian named Rambo sits under a bench." /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Wild beasts abound in Idaho!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the middle of June 2022 I decided to tag along on a cycling trip my aunt had planned, and my parents were going to participate in. Their plan was to ride both the Trail of the Coeur d'Alenes and the Route of the Hiawatha …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04365.jpg" alt="A pomeranian named Rambo sits under a bench." /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Wild beasts abound in Idaho!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the middle of June 2022 I decided to tag along on a cycling trip my aunt had planned, and my parents were going to participate in. Their plan was to ride both the Trail of the Coeur d'Alenes and the Route of the Hiawatha in northern Idaho.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Trusty dog companion rides along in a basket on the back of a bike." src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04381.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Trail of the Coeur d'Alenes Intro&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trail of the Coeur d'Alenes is an old railroad grade that has since been converted for recreational use and does not allow motorized vehicles. It does allow e-bikes though. It is seventy-three miles long and paved the entire way. And while it does require you to cross active roads, but it never shares any road. It crosses most of the state from west to east. It starts in Plummer, Idaho near the southern tip of Lake Coeur d'Alene (it's Chatcolet Lake down there though they're connected) and eventually heads north-east meet and follow I-90 through the historic town of Wallace and on a bit further to end in the town of Mullan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04384.jpg" alt="A pomeranian named Rambo sits in a basket on the back of a bike." /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Ok, last dog photo I swear.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Trail of the Coeur d'Alenes never gets steep. I believe it averages around two percent grade the whole way, with the steepest section from Plummer down to Lake Coeur d'Alene being around three percent grade. Between the four of us, we took three mountain bikes and a cruiser bike with a dog in a basket on the back. Something with road tires would be preferred and recommended for this trail. There are some stretches of bumpy pavement, but certainly not enough to justify a full on mountain bike if you have something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Route of the Hiawatha Intro&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason we brought our mountain bikes though was for the Route of the Hiawatha. This is another old railroad grade that has been converted for recreational use, but unlike the Trail of the Coeur d'Alenes is not paved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though unpaved, the trail still maintains an easy grade, around two percent as well, and boasts seven high trestles and eight tunnels. Each vary in height and length, but the longest tunnel is 1.66 miles long and requires warm clothes and adequate lights. The trail is operated by the Lookout Pass ski area, thought the trail does not start from the ski area. There are a few different places to get on the trail and different ways you can go about riding it. We found it difficult to communicate with Lookout Pass, so I'll do my best to detail the options below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lovely wildflowers in bloom." src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04436.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, on this trail we took our three mountain bikes and the cruiser bike but, since no pets are allowed on this trail, the dog had to be left behind. To elaborate, no pets in any capacity are allowed whether walking on their own or in baskets, trailers, or backpacks. In this case, those of us with the backpacks were glad to have them. The trail is mostly graveled, though with bare dirt stretches and some sections are very bumpy. We all survived, but wider mountain bike tires and suspension were nice to have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Our Campsites&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The campgrounds we stayed at were:
- Heyburn State Park -- Around five miles east of Plummer.
- By The Way Campground -- In Pinehurst, Idaho, just off I-90.
- Wallace RV Park -- Just north of Wallace, Idaho.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each campground offered power and water, and Wallace RV Park had full hookups. I believe By The Way offers full hookups as well, but the site we were in did not have them. Heyburn was wooded and very near to Chatcolet Lake, but still had quite a bit of road noise from the nearby highway five and the big trucks going back and forth for construction taking place. The other two were RV parks and offered little natural shade, though By The Way has a nice gazebo space to take refuge under on hot days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04398.jpg" alt="Riders preparing for a bike ride." /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Preparing for a ride at our campsite at Heyburn State park.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Trail of the Coeur d'Alenes in Depth&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://visitnorthidaho.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/CDA_map3-26-21_updated.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;I would recommend this map&lt;/a&gt;. It is the one we used and the one I'll refer to for mileages, trailheads, and stops. We found paper copies either at Heyburn State Park or the Plummer trailhead. I can't remember which.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way we wound up riding the trail may have been a bit unorthodox, but it worked well for us. Our original plan was to get picked up and dropped off at various points by our fifth member who wasn't riding. This would have let us ride the trail all in one direction. In the end though, we did each day as an out and back. This meant far less driving, and we got to ride the entire trail in both directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Riding along Chatcolet lake with the Chatcolet Lake Bridge in view in the distance." src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04407.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Riding Sections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the sections we broke the trail up into. They worked well since we were riding each section both ways. We only had to drive to Bull Run from Pinehurst but every other day we rode from where we camped. We did the last two sections in the same day with a break in between.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here's a link to the same map I recommended above but with each section we did highlighted in alternating shades of purple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/article_images/2022/06/CDA_map3-26-21_our_route.jpg" target="_blank"&gt;Trail map with our sections highlighted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heyburn to Plummer and Back&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trail mile 6 to trail mile 0.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~6 miles one way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starting direction: Heading East&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heyburn to Springston and Back&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trail mile 6 to 18.3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~12.3 miles one way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starting direction: Heading West&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bull Run to Springston and Back&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trail mile 33.5 to 18.3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~15.2 miles one way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starting direction: Heading East&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pine Creek (Pinehurst) to Bull Run and Back&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trail mile 48.7 to 33.5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~15.2 miles one way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starting direction: Heading East&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pine Creek (Pinehurst) to Shont (Big Creek) and Back&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trail mile 48.7 to 57.4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~8.7 miles one way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starting direction: Heading East&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wallace to Shont (Big Creek) and Back&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trail mile 64.6 to 57.4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~7.2 miles one way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starting Direction: Heading West&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wallace to Mullan and Back&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trail mile 64.6 to 71.4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~6.8 miles one way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starting Direction: Heading East&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Heyburn to Plummer and Back&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trail mile 6 to 0. ~6 miles one way&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our first day was a short one. This was also the steepest section of trail though, so we thought it would be a good way to kick things off and make sure our bikes and legs were working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04388.jpg" alt="A concrete monument in Idaho with flags flying above." /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The monument in Plummer.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We rode from our campsites at Heyburn and took the road through the state park to the trailhead at trail mile six. From there it was a continuous but gentle climb through a forest recovering from a fire alongside a beautiful creek. There were two bathrooms available along this stretch and before long we had climbed out of the woods to flat pavement and the outskirts of the town of Plummer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trailhead at Plummer is very nice with a large parking lot, bathroom, and bike tools. Oh, right, and the giant statue and monument!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04389.jpg" alt="A metal statue of a Native American on a horse." /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;And the statue in Plummer.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a break we headed back down enjoying the easy peddling and coasting now that we were going downhill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Heyburn to Springston (through Harrison)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trail mile 6 to 18.3. ~12.3 miles one way&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Crossing Chatcolet Lake Bridge on a bike." src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04413.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got on the trail at trail mile six again and headed in the opposite direction. And this is a beautiful stretch of trail. There's a mile or two at the start, where you're cruising through the trees and alongside Chatcolet Lake. And then you arrive at, what I considered to be, the highlight of this section, Chatcolet Lake Bridge. It gets high off the water, giving you great views of the lake in all directions and offers a fun descent after you've had your fill and taken your photos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Riding bikes along Lake Coeur d'Alene." src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04426.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of this section is beautiful too. It stays lakeside until you reach Harrison where I highly recommend stopping for ice cream, coffee, sandwiches, or whatever your stomach desires. Ice cream for sure though. Beyond Harrison the trail heads east and gets into marshy terrain that is beautiful in its own right and fantastic for seeing wildlife like herons and moose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A friendly turtle suns itself on a rock." src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04428.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bull Run to Springston&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trail mile 33.5 to 18.3. ~15.2 miles one way&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between the last section and this one we moved campsites. It took around an hour to drive from Heyburn State Park up through Coeur d'Alene to By The Way Campground in Pinehurst. From there it was around a twenty-minute drive back to the Bull Run Trailhead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A wild moose in a marshy meadow." src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04459.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to say this about almost every section. But this one was beautiful as well. You ride along the Coeur d'Alene river for a ways before getting back to marsh land. We managed to start early enough (maybe 8:30 or 9:00) to see several moose, heron, and hear the ruckus caused by a pond full of frogs croaking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A lovely bend in the Coeur d'Alene River." src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04463.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of this section did feel repetitive though too with long straights through the marshes and a headwind that made our return challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pine Creek (Pinehurst) to Bull Run&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trail mile 48.7 to 33.5. ~15.2 miles one way.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="One of many beautiful river views." src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04497.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, this section was my personal favorite. There are long stretches that feel far from roads and follow right along the Coeur d'Alene river. The hills surrounding the trail have closed in more than previous stretches and are growing steeper, but the trail grade remains consistent. We were lucky to spot a couple of bald eagles soaring, and an owl perched in a tree, and had many excuses to step off our bikes and admire the views thanks to plentiful benches and gorgeous bends in the river.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Another lovely view of the Coeur d'Alene River." src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04517.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the weather is hot when you're there (close to 100° in the afternoon the day we did it) then Pine Creek is a wonderful place to cool off. You cross it right at the trailhead and it is very cold! There are many other places along this trail where swimming is not recommended due to high levels of dangerous metals that leached into the water from the mining operations and tailings left behind. I don't know whether this is a safe spot to swim in that regard but we did and don't seem to have any more brain damage than we did before swimming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A heron sitting on a tree branch" src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04528.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pine Creek (Pinehurst) to Shont (Big Creek)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trail mile 48.7 to 60.4. ~11.7 miles one way&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Shont (Big Creek) trailhead is the one just across the freeway from the Sunshine Mine Memorial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This stretch still held some beautiful views and we saw more moose on this stretch than anywhere else. But east of Pinehurst the trail stays closer to I-90 and you pass through Smelterville and Kellogg on the way to the trailhead at trail mile 60.4. All are interesting towns with remarkable history, I just prefer isolated nature when I can get it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04564.jpg" alt="The gazebo at By The Way Campground." /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The gazebo at By The Way Campground.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from nature there were interesting things to see too. Including informative signs discussing the history of mining operations in the area, Silver Mountain Resort, and the Sunshine Mine Memorial which is worth riding over to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This stretch of trail also goes right past the CDA Bike Co. in Kellogg and a Walmart Supercenter in Smelterville if you're in need of any bike parts or snacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wallace to Shont (Big Creek) and Back&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trail mile 64.6 to 57.4. ~7.2 miles one way&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We moved campsites again between the last section and this one from By The Way in Pinehurst to the Wallace RV Park just north of Wallace. We didn't spend that much time exploring the other towns along the way but wandered all over Wallace. Every town in this region has an abundance of history associated with it and Wallace is no different. In fact, the entire town is on the National Historic Register. Just take a look online at the various museums in town and stories about the town, and you'll likely want to visit yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This stretch of trail as well stays close to I-90 and it kind of has to since by this point the surrounding mountains are becoming quite steep. Despite that, riding through the town of Osburn makes for interesting scenery and there's Gene Day Park at the western edge of town that makes for a nice place to stop for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wallace to Mullan and Back&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trail mile 64.6 to 71.4. ~6.8 miles one way&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last stretch on The Trail of the Coeur d'Alenes! Riding under the overpass that towers above Wallace might have been my favorite part of this stretch. On this section there are brief parts where you're right alongside I-90 but fortunately most of it keeps its distance and at least puts some trees between you and the busy freeway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A wild moose on the trail and too close for comfort." src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04566.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the proximity to the road there are still beautiful views on this section as well. You follow the South Fork of the Coeur d'Alene River for a long ways and no matter how you've broken up the trail reaching its end in Mullan is something of a relief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best of luck and have fun if you decide to tackle this gorgeous trail across Idaho! Oh and stay far away from the moose!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04637.jpg" alt="The end of the Trail of the Coeur d'Alenes in Mullan Idaho." /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The end of the Trail of the Coeur d'Alenes in Mullan Idaho.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Route of the Hiawatha in Depth&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I covered some of the details for this trail above. What else do you need to know? We found it to be difficult to get the information we wanted when calling Lookout Pass Ski Resort so I'll try to fill you in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ridethehiawatha.com/trail-maps"&gt;This links to the map I'll be referencing for trail locations.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Entering a tunnel on the Route of the Hiawatha." src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04581.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;General Info&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said above, Lookout Pass manages and operates this trail. There is a fee to ride the trail and they offer a shuttle so that you can do the trail from the top down and get a ride back up. The prices may have changed but I believe the trail fee was $15 per person (on a weekday) when we rode it. We stopped and purchased our passes at the Lookout Pass resort which is on the way to the East Portal trailhead if you're headed there from Wallace. I believe you can purchase passes and rental bikes at the trailhead but am still not certain of this since we didn't so check for yourself before you go!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="In the middle of a tunnel that is short enough to see through." src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04583.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Typical Route&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way I believe most people do the trail is to park at the East Portal, ride the full length of the trail down to Pearson, take the shuttle back to Roland, and the ride back through the very long tunnel (Taft Tunnel [St. Paul Pass]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Riding across an old train trestle high above the ground." src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04586.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;East Portal Parking lot&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look up and download directions before leaving as we did not have cell service out there! But in short,  if you're traveling eastbound on I-90 then shortly after crossing into Montana take exit five. Take a right at the end of the exit ramp, then head left onto the unlabeled Randolph Creek road. You'll then take the first available right and stay right onto Rainy Creek Rd 506. You follow Rainy Creek Rd 506 until turning off it to the left onto what Google Maps labels East Portal Rd where you'll arrive at the parking lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Looking back across an expansive valley at train trestles I had already ridden across." src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04601.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Way We Did It&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We didn't want to take the shuttle and were hoping to ride from the bottom up to have the descent on our way back to our car. We also had a dog that would have to be left in the car and we didn't want to leave him alone for too long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lookout Pass tried to steer us toward doing the trail in the standard fashion I described above and couldn't tell us whether we could drive from the East Portal to Pearson at the other end of the trail. As can be seen on the map, there is a section of trail that is on forest road 506 (described as Rainy Creek Rd 506 above). We had no idea if this section was still open to motor vehicles or not. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Looking further down the same valley as the last photo two more trestles are visible." src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04606.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So our plan was to drive past the East Portal to Roland, where the shuttles return to. Ride from there through the long tunnel to the East Portal and back to check on the dog before doing the rest of the ride from Roland to Pearson and back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What actually happened was, we drove past the East Portal parking area and found the road to be open and in use when we made it to Roland. So, we decided to keep driving. It is a long drive down a windy gravel road but we were able to get all the way to Pearson without difficulty. Do note that there is not a lot of parking down at the Pearson end. My guesstimate would be room for ten cars. It depends on whether people are parked there with trailers and things!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in the end, we rode from the bottom up and then all the way back down and it was great! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And after doing so we drove out forest road 456 back to Wallace which was in fine shape though time consuming since it's another windy and long gravel road. Check first since I don't know for sure if you can buy passes at the Pearson trailhead. But if that is possible you could simply go from Wallace to the Pearson trailhead using forest road 456. I don't know if this is really any faster than driving past the East Portal to Pearson or not so map it and make your own decisions! I'm only going to tell you it's an option. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A high train trestle that, for once, had no people on it." src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04607.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Trail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This trail gets very busy. Hundreds if not thousands of people were out there pedaling on a sunny summer Thursday. Regardless, the views are stunning, there are loads of interesting informative signs and crossing the trestles and riding through the long tunnels make for a ride like no other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do be prepared for the long Taft Tunnel. It's wet and cold in there and it goes on for a long, long ways. You'll want warm layers for that section even if it's a hot day outside. As well, you'll want (they're required) bike lights so you can see where you're riding, and I would recommend taking another flashlight/headlamp so that you can look around the tunnel wherever you please. It's an interesting place! Just do your best not to blind other approaching riders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04609.jpg" alt="A crowd of people looking at a waterfall on the western end of Taft Tunnel." /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A small taste of the crowds of people on the trail that day.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, I don't know if it's always this way. But be prepared for a long wait if you're taking the shuttle back up. I pedaled ahead of my group to free our dog from the car sooner and the lines at the bottom were ridiculously long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, as with any ride, I would recommend bringing the basic tools to work on your bike if necessary. There are 'trail marshalls' who patrol the trail and I believe they will help you with basic repairs in a pinch but carrying what you need is the only sure way to save yourself a long walk if your bike implodes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And again, have fun and good luck if you decide to tackle this trail! It's one I'll never forget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a fantastic trip! We worked hard and had a lot of fun. I had never seen a moose in person before this and am now terrified of their majestic and ungainly speed and power. If you get a chance to ride either of these trails I would highly recommend you take it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/article_images/2022/06/DSC04651.jpg" alt="Looking out from under the I-90 overpass at Wallace Idaho." /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Historic Wallace Idaho.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><category term="January"></category></entry><entry><title>My first post on this new site</title><link href="https://steadytrekker.com/my-first-post-on-this-new-site.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-01-02T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-01-02T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Jeremy Monroe</name></author><id>tag:steadytrekker.com,2023-01-02:/my-first-post-on-this-new-site.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;New Website&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been quite some time but I've finally gotten around to making a new website on which to post my musings and keep track of the outdoor adventures I go on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone wondering, I've decided to build this site using the Python based static site generator …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;New Website&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been quite some time but I've finally gotten around to making a new website on which to post my musings and keep track of the outdoor adventures I go on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone wondering, I've decided to build this site using the Python based static site generator Pelican. That means I don't have to deal with backend programming and can focus on frontend development and writing. Better yet I can easily write my posts using Markdown syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if none of that makes sense to you don't worry. It doesn't really matter. My plan for this site is still to post the photos I take and write about the places I visit. Not talk about the technical details of my website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now this is all. But hopefully I'll be back with more soon!
I plan to bring the posts from my old website to this one over time but it's a tedious process to change the file paths for all the images so we'll see when I get around to that.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Test"></category></entry><entry><title>Three High Passes Trek - Pt 6</title><link href="https://steadytrekker.com/three-high-passes-trek-pt-6.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-11-05T12:48:05-08:00</published><updated>2018-11-05T12:48:05-08:00</updated><author><name>Jeremy Monroe</name></author><id>tag:steadytrekker.com,2018-11-05:/three-high-passes-trek-pt-6.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having arrived in Namche I felt an overwhelming sense of relief and accomplishment. I had technically gotten back on track with my original trekking plan when we made it to Phakding but Namche was my focus and goal since we began. In turn, I began to feel a bit lost …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having arrived in Namche I felt an overwhelming sense of relief and accomplishment. I had technically gotten back on track with my original trekking plan when we made it to Phakding but Namche was my focus and goal since we began. In turn, I began to feel a bit lost as well. I knew I had to determine what destination to focus on next before I completely lost my sense of direction. I was already tired and homesick and a part of me wanted nothing more than to call it quits and head back to the relative comfort of Kathmandu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-959" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181010_072705.jpg" alt="Sunrise over Namche. I can't remember what peak that is." /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Sunrise over Namche. I can't remember what peak that is.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I couldn't allow myself to do this. I have a paper itinerary with my entire route planned and once it's on paper I'm pretty good at sticking to it. So I showered, ate well, and made the most of our rest day with Sanjey, Niclas, and Ujjal. We went for a short walk to a nearby Everest viewpoint and discovered not only our first views of Everest and Lhotse but a museum dedicated to Sagarmatha National Park and a statue of Tenzing Norgay as well. We spent a while there taking photos, learning about the park, and watching as the clouds gathered and cleared around the peaks of the highest mountains in the world. From here they still looked distant, unattainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-960" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181010_110255.jpg" alt="Tenzing Norgay statue with cloud covered Everest and Lhotse behind." /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Tenzing Norgay statue with cloud covered Everest and Lhotse behind.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before too long my antsy nature took hold and I suggested a few times to my relaxing friends that we head down to town for errands and lunch. I had laundry done in Kathmandu and didn't realize until well after the fact that they hadn't returned one of my socks. So, with the intention of acquiring a fresh pair and stocking up on snacks before getting too far into the middle of nowhere the four of us left the hilltop in the direction of town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A short while and a lot of wandering later and I had procured a new pair of socks for three hundred rupees, additional snacks to feed my endless appetite, and a bag of black tea to avoid the increasing teahouse tea prices. By now we were starving and unsure where to eat. The main restaurants in Namche are all touristy and accordingly expensive. Not wanting to pay exorbitant prices and hoping to find more authentic food Sanjey and I spurred the group to further exploration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We headed towards a place I had seen the day before. A dingy home restaurant that reeked of alcohol and lacked any cleanliness or lighting. We were told the only thing being served were veg momos and we would have ordered some if not for an inflated foreigner price procured from thin air by the proprietor. Disgruntled we left without further negotiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-961" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181010_120413.jpg" alt="Panorama of Namche Bazaar" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Panorama of Namche Bazaar&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ujjal told us of a spot he had gone the day before with inexpensive and delicious plates of momos. Quickly in agreement, we headed towards the place keeping our eyes peeled for anywhere else with reasonable prices and a bit more variety. The spot we wound up at was fittingly titled 'The Momo Center', considering the only thing they served were buff momos for 150 rupees per plate. It was someone's kitchen and bedroom combined. Unperturbed we ordered a plate apiece and sat outside on a nearby stone wall as they were prepared. Our first plates disappeared in seconds and considering the low price compared to Namche standards we all ordered more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had shopped and eaten and without anything else to do in town but spend more money, we headed back to our hotel. I had intended to hike to Hotel Everest View on this day off to aid the acclimatization process but had written it off due to fatigue and disinterest from the rest of the group. No one wanted to do a steep, strenuous climb straight up the hillside behind Namche. I nearly didn't but it was on my itinerary, and I have a hard time sitting around for long. So, at the last minute, I threw the bare necessities in my day back and headed out the door. It was already 3:30 pm so I didn't have that much light left, but by myself and without my full pack I moved quickly up the hill savoring the increasingly beautiful views of Namche from above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-962" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181010_171355-e1541348440247.jpg" alt="Looking down the trail towards Namche and beyond." /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Looking down the trail towards Namche and beyond.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little more than an hour later I arrived at the hotel. Confusion was my first reaction. Surrounded by trees the unassuming hotel sits on top of a rise in the middle of nowhere with nothing more than a footpath leading to it. It's clearly a quality hotel and if not for the afternoon fog the views would have been incredible. I had read previously that rooms go for around $200 per night but at that time didn't know the history of the place and couldn't begin to understand who, with that kind of money, would make the journey to stay there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-963" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181010_164422.jpg" alt="Out front of Hotel Everest View. The highest I had ever been at that time. 12,729'" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Out front of Hotel Everest View. The highest I had ever been at that time. 12,729'&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I later found out that the hotel was built by Japanese entrepreneurs along with the nearby Syangboche airport. When the hotel opened in 1973 the intention was that tourists would be able to fly into the nearby airstrip and with minimal effort have fantastic views of Everest, Lhotse, Ama Dablam, and all those other snowy peaks. Apparently, flying directly to 12,600 feet makes for awful altitude symptoms and it wasn't until a few deaths occurred that there was government intervention and the airstrip was shut down. Without flights to Syangboche, the only option left to tourists is making the walk from Lukla. &lt;a href="https://www.derelictplaces.co.uk/main/overseas-sites/6964-everest-view-hotel-nepal-aug-08-a.html#.W9qX6ZMzYU4"&gt;This info thanks to derelictplaces.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I entered the hotel and wandered around a bit. The dining area and hallways were empty except for staff. I went to the north side of the building and out onto a large equally empty deck. The clouds and fog were too thick for any view so I took a quick look around and began the walk back down hoping to finish the descent before dark. I can move pretty fast so it wasn't long before I was looking down on Namche at sunset. Feeling good without weight on my back I made quick work of the stairs down and made it back with light to spare. The first of many 'rest days' where I would still climb and descend well over 1000 feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-966" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181010_172225.jpg" alt="Porters on their way to Namche." /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Porters on their way to Namche.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An easier but still trying day had come to a close. I was tired but satisfied with myself and all too ready to get out of civilization and deeper into the mountains. Our next destination would be Tengboche and after all the distance we had already covered it was hard to believe that this trek still wasn't even halfway through. My ravenous appetite led me back to dhal baht for dinner with the obligatory heaping second helping of rice, curried vegetables, and lentil soup and shortly after to my comfy bed. I fell asleep wondering how any of this would be accomplishable without the fantastic luxury of teahouse accommodations along the way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Nepal"></category></entry><entry><title>Three High Passes Trek - Pt 5</title><link href="https://steadytrekker.com/three-high-passes-trek-pt-5.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-11-01T17:08:50-07:00</published><updated>2018-11-01T17:08:50-07:00</updated><author><name>Jeremy Monroe</name></author><id>tag:steadytrekker.com,2018-11-01:/three-high-passes-trek-pt-5.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've heard of plenty of people going from Lukla to Namche Bazaar in one day but let me tell you, even from Phakding, halfway between the two it's no easy feat. Maybe it was because of the four previous, strenuous days, but our journey to Namche seemed to go on …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've heard of plenty of people going from Lukla to Namche Bazaar in one day but let me tell you, even from Phakding, halfway between the two it's no easy feat. Maybe it was because of the four previous, strenuous days, but our journey to Namche seemed to go on forever. The day began well enough. Breakfast with our new friends Niclas and Ujjal and excitement to be making real progress towards our goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-933" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02704.jpg" alt="First glimpse of mountains leaving Phakding" &gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;First glimpse of mountains leaving Phakding&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="wp-image-934 size-large" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02709.jpg" alt="A busy suspension bridge crossing." &gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;A busy bridge crossing. It's a bit blurry but I'm ok with it.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got going around eight o'clock, hopping in line on the trail with hundreds of other tourists. I discovered that hiking in an endless slow-moving line simply doesn't work for me and it wasn't long before I was passing everyone possible, leaving my friends behind. I stopped around nine-thirty for an early tea break, both to calm my nerves and thinking we could all regroup. But I still hadn't seen friendly faces by the time my cup was empty and continued on alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-935" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02713.jpg" alt="The view where I stopped for tea." &gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;The view where I stopped for tea.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first hurdle that day was a small one. Getting the 2000 rupee local permit near Monjo was a quick and painless process. Many people stood around blocking through traffic but there wasn't any line at the permit window so I paid and pushed my way through the crowd to keep moving. Maybe ten minutes later I reached the entrance to Sagarmatha National Park. Another stop for a 3390 rupee permit is necessary here and wound up being much more of an ordeal than the local permit. I'm not sure if there's a better name for the local permit, but that's what I heard it referred to as. Most travelers pick this up as they leave Lukla. Apparently, most travelers make their flight to Lukla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-936" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181009_101536.jpg" alt="Welcome to Sagarmatha National park"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, the entrance to the National Park is just over the crest of a hill. You descend steps to a nice courtyard. Or what would have been a nice courtyard except when I arrived it was full of what must have been hundreds of people. Mostly standing around or sitting and waiting. Two ticket windows had lines of about thirty people each and at first glance, the situation seemed hectic but not downright miserable. It turns out the guides take the paperwork and money for each of their patrons and get ten to forty permits for the national park at once. This should speed things up, but the process is severely limited by the fact that each ticket window only has one person handwriting each permit with a copy for the visitor and a receipt for the park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-937" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181009_101544.jpg" alt="The crowds wait to enter Sagarmatha National Park" &gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;The crowds wait to enter Sagarmatha National Park&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe thirty minutes later my friends arrived and I had them hand me each of their local permits, passports, and the requisite cash. Maybe an hour and a half after that I was finally at the window, pushing my way between Nepali guides trying to take my place, as I handed over our documents and money. While the park employees filled out the necessary fields on our permits I managed to snap a picture of their board with the recorded number of visitors since 1998. I've attempted to crop them down to make things easier to read but it may still be impossible to make out on a small screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-931" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181009_111735.jpg" alt="Visitor count sagarmatha from 1998 to 2016" &gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-932" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181009_111735-2.jpg" alt="Visitor count sagarmatha 2017 to 2018 and beyond" &gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can't make out the numbers the part I find interesting is that there was a slow climb from about 20,000 visitors in 1998 to 37,000 in 2016. Then however in 2017, the number jumped to 50,000 visitors! I haven't taken the time to figure out what percentage increase this is but it seems substantial. I can only imagine 2018 will result in a similar or higher count based on the crowds I witnessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting stuff. To continue with the story though, we received our permits, managed to get all our papers and change back, and graciously feasted on Toblerone chocolate provided by Sanjey (I just realized I've been misspelling your name until now Sanj. I don't know if you're reading this, but sorry about that!) to keep our spirits up. A quick check-in at the nearby police booth with our new permits and we were on our way through the gate and into Sagarmatha National Park!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-938" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181009_115402.jpg" alt="Some woman at the actual park entrance." &gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Some woman at the actual park entrance.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The park entrance is a stone step descent to a suspension bridge and the village of Jarsalle. All the groups stop for lunch after the park entrance and despite our hunger, we were unwilling to stop at the incredibly crowded restaurants only a few minutes after getting through. The decision was made to stop before Namche at a village that was clearly labeled on our paper map as existing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-939" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181009_121120.jpg" alt="Looking back at the park entrance from Jorsalle" &gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Looking back at the park entrance from Jarsalle&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We left Jorsalle and continued our trek following the trail as it meanders along a dry creek bed following a river for a while. It was during this section while checking the route on my phone that I noticed something missing. No village, or any dwellings at all, showed up between us and Namche. A guide confirmed it for us, no villages, no real stops at all between us and our destination. Just a big climb taking us from 8989 feet at Jorsalle to 11,286 feet at Namche Bazaar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-940" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181009_125109.jpg" alt="A portrait of myself with two high bridges behind me."&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Two high bridges&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After easily following the creek bed for a ways the trail came to a beautiful viewpoint where two rivers joined and two suspension bridges were visible. One hanging high above the other. The trail took a turn straight up the hill and it didn't take long to realize we would be headed for one of the bridges. Whether it would be the higher or lower one was as yet unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-942" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02723.jpg" alt="The trail gets steep heading to the high bridges" &gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;The trail gets steep heading to the high bridges&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mild fear of heights left me hoping for the lower bridge but of course, we promptly climbed past a sign saying this bridge was closed and watched the upper bridge grow closer as we struggled up the trail. I was in luck though. We arrived at the highest suspension bridge I've ever seen and it wasn't crowded. No one was in the process of leading a yak or donkey train across and there weren't more than ten other tourists crossing at the moment so I gritted my teeth and started walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;video width="1280" height="720" controls="true" loop="true"&gt;
&lt;source src="/images/article_images/2018/10/Bridge-Clip_Medium.mp4" &gt;
&lt;/video&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not wanting to miss anything on this fabulous journey I forced myself to stop in the middle of the bridge and look all around, including straight down. Not long enough to take photos, but long enough to soak in the view and building adrenaline. I crossed without incidence and reveled in the elation I felt on the other side at the same time. I put out of my mind the fact that this bridge was the only way back down from the mountains and decided instead to use it as once more excuse to trek slowly and put off another crossing for as long as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-943" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02733.jpg" alt="Niclas was having a good time on the high bridge"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Niclas was having a good time on the high bridge&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We regrouped, watched yaks, donkeys, foreigners, and porters all cross this crazy bridge and then reconciled ourselves to the fact that our climb had really only just begun. A couple of hours and we nearly made it to Namche. I had found myself a short way ahead of the group again when a police permit checkpoint appeared. I had learned from before and got in line as fast as I could. Of course, this checkpoint was destined to take an inordinate amount of time as well. I stood, growing more frustrated, as a man entered our information, into a computer this time, typing away with only two fingers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-944" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02744.jpg" alt="Looking down on the high bridges." &gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Looking down on the high bridges.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again my friends caught up and we waited in the cold to have our information recorded. After freezing a bit we climbed the last, fortunately short, stretch to Namche and began ascending through the city looking for rooms. With the recent influx of tourists, most everywhere was booked. We tried several lodges with no luck accepting as we continued the difficult climb through the city that we would likely have to split up. The daylight was fading along with our energy when we got lucky and found a nice hotel with a couple of open rooms. A bit of bargaining facilitated by Ujjal and we talked the caretaker down to 3000 rupees for two nights instead of 2500 per night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="wp-image-945 size-large" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181009_162026.jpg" alt="The view of Namche from near our hotel. A bit foggy." &gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;The view of Namche from our hotel. A bit foggy.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, they only had one double room and one single room left and at 1500 rupees per night they cost more than Ujjal wanted to spend anyways. He left to find his own accommodations with our assurance that he could come back to use our power outlets and hot shower. This place was luxurious, our own bathroom, a shower with hot water, power outlets in our room, and a great view of Namche from above. It was well worth the higher price, especially since it only came to 750 rupees a night split between myself and Sanjey. Less than I had been paying for a private hotel room in Kathmandu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all met up for a large dinner, took long showers, and let our weary bodies rest, eagerly anticipating our first 'rest day' after five hard days of trekking.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Nepal"></category></entry><entry><title>Three High Passes Trek - Pt 4</title><link href="https://steadytrekker.com/three-high-passes-trek-pt-4.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-31T20:25:38-07:00</published><updated>2018-10-31T20:25:38-07:00</updated><author><name>Jeremy Monroe</name></author><id>tag:steadytrekker.com,2018-10-31:/three-high-passes-trek-pt-4.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Our next day began from Karikhola at around 6600 feet. I knew there was a big climb ahead of us and after the last couple days was mentally prepared for something strenuous. We planned to make it to the town of Surke that day which would put us just below …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Our next day began from Karikhola at around 6600 feet. I knew there was a big climb ahead of us and after the last couple days was mentally prepared for something strenuous. We planned to make it to the town of Surke that day which would put us just below Lukla and more or less back on track for our goals of getting to Everest Base Camp and crossing the Three High Passes along the way. Other guides had told us getting from Kharikola to Surke would be manageable and other trekkers had similar plans so our hopes were high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-915" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02589.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Looking back on Kharikola. The monastery is the red building on the right.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After heading out of town the climb began in earnest. Evermore of the stone steps lead up the hillside to Bhupsa and beyond. I like to climb and it wasn't long before Sanjay was lost to sight behind me. I made my way up and up to about 9600 feet where the trail levels off and more or less maintain its elevation while winding around the hillside into yet another valley. I was feeling strong and eager to get places so I pushed myself onward, around the mountain, postponing lunch until I arrived in Puiya around two o'clock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-917" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181007_150201.jpg" alt="The rooms at the Beehive Lodge" /&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;The rooms at the Beehive Lodge&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the last couple of days, we knew I was the faster hiker and had already decided Puiya would be a good place to meet up if we became separated. I found a nice little spot for lunch and settled in. A couple I had passed on the trail showed up soon after I arrived. The guy, whose name I've forgotten, was just getting over stomach issues and they decided to scratch their plan for getting to Surke that day and stay in Puiya instead. My weary legs and full stomach convinced me of the same and I made the decision to stay for the night as well. Rooms at the Beehive lodge went side by side up a steep hill with the dining room down near the trail. All in all a cozy place. They even had a hutch full of cute rabbits. But I have to assume those were for eating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;video width="1920" height="1080" loop="true" controls='true'&gt;
    &lt;source src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181007_150413.mp4" type="video/mp4"&gt; 
&lt;/video&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow that night all the small groups of trekkers decided to stay at the same lodge. People we'd interacted with repeatedly on the trail were suddenly sharing a dining room with us and boy did we have fun. We got to know better three people from Poland we had talked to several times already, met a father and son from America on their way to EBC, and made two friends I won't soon forget. Ujjal from India and Niclas from Germany. We got to talking that evening and being we were all going the same way headed to bed with the expectation of meeting again soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="wp-image-919 size-large" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02618.jpg" alt="A grumpy cat in Puiya" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;A grumpy cat in Puiya&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A restful night filled with good conversation and better food saw us back on the trail with the intention of making it to Phakding and back on track to fulfill our plans for Everest Basecamp and the three high passes. This day began much easier. Puiya to Surke is mostly downhill though none of the trails in Nepal are actually flat. We ran into Ujjal and Niclas again at the top of the final climb before a long descent to Surke. From the high point on the corner of a ridge, we were finally able to catch our first glimpse of Lukla and see a few planes land on the infamous runway. Of course, I missed all photo opportunities for planes landing in the distance, but here's Sanjay climbing a hill and Niclas looking down on Surke anyways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-920" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02644.jpg" alt="Sanjay climbing a hill with a donkey train leading the way" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Sanjay climbing a hill with a donkey train leading the way&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="wp-image-921 size-large" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02651.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Niclas looking down on the village of Surke&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The four of us hiked down to Surke and by chance stopped for lunch at the same place as our Polish friends. Shortly after the Americans rolled in too. Sanjay and I got to know Niclas and Ujjal better and decided to hike with them for the day since they were trying to make it to Phakding as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-922" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02657.jpg" alt="Some flowery plant. Maybe a rhododendron?" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Is this a rhododendron?!&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was all uphill from Surke. Seriously, this was the lowest point we would reach for the rest of our trek and the trail let us know with another steep climb out of town that continued as we made our way towards the main EBC trail. We found a canine companion along the way, a cute fluffy dog who was inclined to follow us and act like a goofball doing his best to infuriate any donkeys going in the other direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-923" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02659.jpg" alt="A cute dog who followed us for a ways." /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Our fluffy companion&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The five of us stuck together for a time but were eventually separated by a suspension bridge where our friendly dog was too scared to cross. He would get fifteen feet onto it, lay down, and cry. Despite attempts to help him across our fluffy companion was left behind with his cries echoing around the corner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-924" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02661.jpg" alt="Sanjay and Ujjal trying to convince the dog to cross the bridge."  /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Sanjay and Ujjal trying to convince the dog to cross the bridge.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saddened by our loss we continued up the hill and into a rustic village with extraordinary boulders and small caves in abundance. This town still had its authenticity despite its proximity to the main trekking trail and we caught our last glimpse of rural Nepali life before running into the masses. Around the corner, we would make it to Cheplung and with it the main trail for Everest base camp coming from Lukla and continuing into the wilderness towards Phakding and Namche Bazaar. Like night and day, after connecting to the main trail we went from seeing only the occasional passerby to passing massive groups and getting stuck in endless lines of foreigners, local porters, donkeys, and yaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-925" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02677.jpg" alt="Donkeys cross a small bridge"  /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Donkey's cross a small bridge&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-926" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02681.jpg" alt="Niclas looks into an old stone dwelling." /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Someone's old stone dwelling.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What felt like ages later we arrived in Phakding, excited to be back on track, but discouraged by the hordes of people and the resulting dissatisfactory accommodations. Feeling we had overpaid for cramped, not so clean rooms I reassured myself it was only for one night and went to have dinner with new friends as we made plans for the following days.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Nepal"></category></entry><entry><title>Three High Passes Trek - Pt 3</title><link href="https://steadytrekker.com/three-high-passes-trek-pt-3.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-26T17:06:43-07:00</published><updated>2018-10-26T17:06:43-07:00</updated><author><name>Jeremy Monroe</name></author><id>tag:steadytrekker.com,2018-10-26:/three-high-passes-trek-pt-3.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, I'm way behind now. Between poor cell reception and expensive charging fees, I was using my phone as little as possible while trekking. I'm done now, back in Kathmandu, and will be releasing the rest of these posts more or less as quickly as I can write them. This …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, I'm way behind now. Between poor cell reception and expensive charging fees, I was using my phone as little as possible while trekking. I'm done now, back in Kathmandu, and will be releasing the rest of these posts more or less as quickly as I can write them. This one has been saved in my phone for a few weeks but didn't feel finished enough to publish. So, here's your chance to get a more in-depth look at the trek I completed and what life on popular trails in Nepal is like. It already feels a bit strange looking back on this experience, but, back to the story with me and Sanjay's second day of trekking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-903 aligncenter" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02553.jpg" alt=""/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a restful night in Taksindu, I started the day early by heading back to the monastery to take photos at sunrise. I heard the monks in chanting for their morning prayer but didn't feel like taking part today so I took my pictures and sat in their courtyard for a while taking in the scene before heading back to our lodge.  Sanjay was up by the time I returned and after a breakfast of hot muesli, it was time to get back onto the trail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter wp-image-904 size-large" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02556.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting off from town proved to be a bit trickier than anticipated. On our previous day there only seemed to be one trail and good signage to lead us onward. This morning there were several unlabeled trails leaving town and it took careful consultation of maps on both our phones and eventually the guides of the Australian group giving us a handy pointer to get us going in the right direction. From my phone maps, I knew our day involved a large amount of descending but was thoroughly unprepared for what was in store. Taksindu La, the pass we crossed the day before sits around 10,000 feet. The village of Taksindu is a bit lower, around 9600 feet. But before reaching our destination we would have to cross a river and pass through the village of Jubhing at an elevation of 4800 feet dropping 4800 feet in about five miles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-906 aligncenter" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02568.jpg" alt="Looking down on the village of Nunthalla from above." /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To lose elevation so quickly the trail consists of stone steps nearly the whole way down and was slippery due to rainy afternoons and copious amounts of donkey crap. My dreams of quickly covering distance going downhill evaporated after the first couple of miles took as many hours to cover. Knees aching we continued down and down and down, following a single track trail and occasionally crossing the road in progress being built to eventually connect Phaplu to Lukla. Normally I would avoid roads and take single track at any chance I can get. In this case, I began to wonder why we were putting so much strain on our knees rather than walking the relatively level road. We stopped at one point and asked a local whether the trail and road went to the same place. He told us the trail is a shortcut, fastest way to get down the hill. Keeping this in mind we still decided to hop on the road the next time we crossed it. Maybe covering more distance, but making the walking suddenly feel effortless in comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly after getting onto the road we discovered a small, tucked away temple. It seemed to have signs of Buddhism and Hinduism including stones and spears for Shiva. We spent some time soaking in the wonder of a very old site and replenished our energy with the snacks given to us by the monks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter wp-image-907 size-large" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02577.jpg" alt="A hidden temple in rural Nepal with prayer flags crossing it." /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The views were fantastic, the trails uncrowded, our spirits undampened and it wasn't long before we passed through the wonderful village of Nunthala. Neither of us felt like stopping for lunch yet but as we passed through the town an old man going the other way stopped us for a somewhat nonsensical conversation. He attempted to explain to us the meaning of bistari bistari. Our understanding was still flawed when we left him but we would hear this phrase repeatedly as we went and found out it means slowly, slowly. Walk slowly, ascend slowly, maybe just live slowly. Excellent advice for the trails around here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-908 aligncenter" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02579.jpg" alt="Tattered prayer flags still hang" /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving Nunthala the weather seemed to be moving in and it wasn't long before thunder could be heard in the distance and occasional drizzle began. I put on my rain cover and we continued on hoping for shelter and food without too much delay. Just as the downpour began in earnest we stumbled upon a small lodge and lunch spot with an excellent covered outdoor seating area. Our lunch was spent over dhal baht and milk tea as we enjoyed conversation with three guides on their way to meet clients in Lukla and also hiding from the worst of the storm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="wp-image-909 size-large" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02585.jpg" alt="Sanjay waits for lunch while it rains." /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Sanjay waits for lunch while it rains&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this took place before we even reached the bottom of the valley. Eventually, the river grew louder and the bottom of the valley came into sight. We passed through a small village, no more than a lodge and a couple of homes, and crossed our first suspension bridge. A light rain began as we started the lengthy climb to Karikhola. Unsure whether the weather would get worse we debated stopping in Jubhing for the night. A few minutes under an overhung rock while it rained hard for a few minutes and the decision to continue was made for us as the rain abruptly let up again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-910" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181029_103219.jpg" alt="The first suspension bridge we came to near the village of Jubhing" /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way from Jubhing to Kharikola consists of around 2000 feet of gain in just over two miles. Thus we found ourselves climbing up steep stone steps so similar to the ones we had just spent the morning climbing down. A long couple of hours later and we crested the ridge on which Karikhola resides. From the town, the trail onward is visible climbing up and up, cresting another ridge on its way to Kari La, the next pass we would have to cross on our way to our destination. This sight left me with the realization that trekking in Nepal was going to be no easy feat, regardless of the elevation. I made some adjustments to my expectations for each day and settled into the fact that the going would be slow and difficult and each destination on the map further apart than they appeared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="size-large wp-image-912" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/DSC02609.jpg" alt="Steep stone stairs climb ever upwards" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Stone steps climb ever upwards&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put this out of my mind, visited the local monastery, ate more fantastic food, and once again fell asleep nearly before my head touched the pillow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="wp-image-913 size-large" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181006_163642.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;The monastery at Kharikola&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content><category term="Nepal"></category></entry><entry><title>Three High Passes Trek - Pt 2</title><link href="https://steadytrekker.com/three-high-passes-trek-pt-2.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-11T18:21:05-07:00</published><updated>2018-10-11T18:21:05-07:00</updated><author><name>Jeremy Monroe</name></author><id>tag:steadytrekker.com,2018-10-11:/three-high-passes-trek-pt-2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I heard many estimates for the time it would take to trek from Phaplu to Lukla. I was told two days by several people as well as three to five days by others. Three to five days is accurate. As I write this I've walked three full days and likely …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I heard many estimates for the time it would take to trek from Phaplu to Lukla. I was told two days by several people as well as three to five days by others. Three to five days is accurate. As I write this I've walked three full days and likely could make it to Lukla tomorrow though we'll be bypassing it to head straight for Cheplung and higher up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only 28 miles separate Phaplu and Lukla but high passes and deep valleys make for challenging days up and down slippery stone steps. Expect to ascend and descend multiple thousands of feet each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter wp-image-883 size-full" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181005_144313-01383734505523804091.jpg" alt="A yak in the middle of the trail" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;The first of many yaks to come.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get back to our original itineraries Sanjay and I hiked from Phaplu to Taksindu, to Karikhola, to Pouiya, to Phakding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To elaborate, Phaplu resides right around 8000 feet. A comfortable starting elevation and a nice little town that will give you your first views of snow-capped peaks if the weather is clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaving the town on foot we walked on a road for nearly seven miles. Winding our way in and out of valleys as we slowly climbed towards the trail coming from Jiri.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly after connecting to the trail from Jiri we arrived at Ringmu. Rain threatened and we went back and forth deciding whether to push our luck or stay dry in the lodges at Ringmu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-884" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/img_20181008_135243_4676618211914412203577.jpg" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;We stopped for lunch and found a friend.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drizzle that had begun quickly abated and we began the steep climb to Taksindu La. Our first pass sitting around 10,000 feet. Arriving at this pass on our first day was an exhausting but gratifying moment. It felt as though our trek had really begun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our original hope was to continue down a massive descent past the village of Taksindu to Nuthalla or beyond. However, as our weary feet carried us into Taksindu, already 500 feet lower than the pass, we discovered a beautiful monastery perched there and in the end made the decision to stop to visit it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found fantastic accommodations nearby in a newer lodge with an all-wood interior and spacious rooms. Relieved and ecstatic we unpacked our belongings and made the short walk back up to the monastery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-885" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181005_155923-013637252931809846686.jpg" width="3000" height="2250" data-temp-aztec-id="641b0d5e-8470-41c9-a4e0-3d841b176df8" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;First glimpse of the Buddhist monastery&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unbeknownst to me it turns out Buddhist monks are happy to have visitors and welcome you to sit in on their evening prayer chant. We arrived shortly after they began and stuck around for the full forty five minute session as they chanted, played drums, cymbals, and horns, and filled the room with incense smoke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We talked briefly with one of them before leaving though in a state of meditative shock I wasn't sure what to ask or say and simply thanked him repeatedly for allowing our participation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That night we got a taste of a real teahouse. Eating dinner in the communal dining area around a wood stove we met a group all from Australia visiting a school they donate to and picking up trash along their trekking route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day I was exhausted but so satisfied to be moving. I had no idea how difficult the next few days would turn out to be and slept soundly anticipating a continuation of an excellent adventure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Nepal"></category></entry><entry><title>Three High Passes Trek - Pt 1</title><link href="https://steadytrekker.com/three-high-passes-trek-pt-1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-11T07:51:22-07:00</published><updated>2018-10-11T07:51:22-07:00</updated><author><name>Jeremy Monroe</name></author><id>tag:steadytrekker.com,2018-10-11:/three-high-passes-trek-pt-1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So much has taken place since my last post. Not many days have passed, but I've found myself in many different places and have interacted with many different people. I'm exhausted but happy and looking forward to the next stages of my journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start from the beginning, just a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So much has taken place since my last post. Not many days have passed, but I've found myself in many different places and have interacted with many different people. I'm exhausted but happy and looking forward to the next stages of my journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start from the beginning, just a few days ago I found myself sitting in the domestic section of the Tribhuvan airport. Learning to navigate the chaos, getting no service, and still feeling optimistic about my flight to Lukla.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seven hours later and my feelings had degraded drastically. In response to poor weather at Lukla, I had changed my flight to Phaplu. We boarded a plane around 3:30 pm with the news that Lukla airport had opened and we would be headed there or Phaplu if the weather turned. Instead, we got into the air and were forced to turn around after only about twenty minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this disappointment I headed back the next morning for another full day of incessant announcements, dashed hopes, and confusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This day turned out to be quite productive. I met my new friend Sanjay who happened to have a flexible schedule and an inclination to skip out on our flights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That evening on our way back to our hotel in Kathmandu we ran into a man I had talked to before who informed us of his friend's ability to hire a jeep to Phaplu for us. We quickly made the decision to take this route, canceled our plane tickets, and negotiated a price for transport to the jeep station the next morning and the jeep ticket itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, we paid 4200 Nepali rupees. Approximately $35, for an 11-hour jeep ride far into the Nepal countryside. Our jeep held ten passengers and the driver. A space that would have been comfortable with eight passengers was quite cramped. Everyone pressed together with one unfortunate passenger in the way back unable to sit fully on the seat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class="wp-image-876 aligncenter size-full" src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181004_113700-017426464850623505987.jpg" alt="A dirt road in rural Nepal."&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;I was unaware of this at the time. But after leaving this pitstop we would climb the ridge in the center of this photo. Looking closely you can just make out the single lane, guardrail-less road way up there.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The roads initially were quite good. Paved with only the occasional terrible section. After about 5 hours, including two breaks for food, things began to get crazier. We started to climb into the mountains and the road varied between poorly maintained pavement and dirt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We climbed until the road straddled a ridge, dropping off thousands of feet on either side and continued winding up and down through the mountains passing and being passed by other vehicles on what should have been considered a one-lane road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we continued, our journey became more of a 4x4 excursion than a drive. Shortly before Salleri, the road became a single lane muddy track littered with deep ruts, steep climbs, and rocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly before our arrival it began to pour down rain, spirits dampened along with our gear on the roof we pulled into Salleri. A couple of passengers had to unload here but fortunately for us the rain lessened by the time we arrived in Phaplu two miles up the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="/images/article_images/2018/10/20181004_174830-013880986841790107019.jpg"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Looking out over Phaplu after a long, long day.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exhausted from a long day we found a nice place to stay, got dinner and quickly fell asleep anticipating a fresh start the next day as well as our first day of trekking.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Nepal"></category></entry></feed>